I'm a huge believer in hands-on education.
أن مؤمنة جداً بضرورة التعليم " العملي "
But you have to have the right tools.
ولكن ان كنا نملك الادوات الصحيحة لذلك
If I'm going to teach my daughter about electronics,
اذا كنت بصدد تعليم إبنتي الالكترونيات
I'm not going to give her a soldering iron.
فلن أعطيها " كاوي القصدير "
And similarly, she finds prototyping boards
وبنفس الطريقة .. ان عملية نسخ \ نقل ما كتب على السبورة
really frustrating for her little hands.
هو مرهق جداً لها !
So my wonderful student Sam and I
لذا قمت انا وطالبي الرائع " سام "
decided to look at the most tangible thing we could think of:
بالنظر الى اكثر شيء واقعي يمكننا القيام به
Play-Doh.
بصلصال اللعب
And so we spent a summer
وقد قضينا الصيف بأكمله
looking at different Play-Doh recipes.
نطالع وصفات صناعة الصلصال " عجينة اللعب "
And these recipes probably look really familiar
وهذه الوصفات معروفة لكل من
to any of you who have made homemade play-dough --
حاول ان يصنع صلصال لعب في المنزل
pretty standard ingredients you probably have in your kitchen.
انه مكونات اساسية يملكها عادة الفرد في مطبخه
We have two favorite recipes --
لقد خرجنا بوصفتين مفضلتين
one that has these ingredients
واحدة تحوي هذه المكونات
and a second that had sugar instead of salt.
والثانية تحوي السكر بدلاً من الملح
And they're great. We can make great little sculptures with these.
وهي رائعة جداً .. يمكن ان تصنع " مجسمات \ نماذج " بواسطة هذا الصلصال
But the really cool thing about them is when we put them together.
والامر الرائع بهذا الخصوص .. هو عندما تضعهما معاً
You see that really salty Play-Doh?
يمكنكم ان تروا اللعب بصلصال اللعب " ذا وصفة الملح "
Well, it conducts electricity.
الذي هو موصل جيد للكهرباء
And this is nothing new.
وهذه ليست بمعلومات جديدة
It turns out that regular Play-Doh that you buy at the store conducts electricity,
لقد تبين لنا ان معجون الصلصال الذي نشتريه من المتاجر " مُوصل للكهرباء "
and high school physics teachers have used that for years.
وقد استخدمه الفيزيائين والمدرسين لعدة سنوات
But our homemade play-dough
ولكن صلصالنا المنزلي
actually has half the resistance of commercial Play-Doh.
والذي يملك نصف صلابة صلصال اللعب
And that sugar dough?
ماذا عن الصلصال السكري ؟
Well it's 150 times more resistant to electric current
حسناً .. انه مقاوم للكهرباء 150 مرة اكثر من
than that salt dough.
الصلصال الملحي
So what does that mean?
ماذا يعني هذا ؟
Well it means if you them together you suddenly have circuits --
يعني اننا ان وضعناهم سويةً
circuits that the most creative, tiny, little hands
فاننا نحصل على دارة كهربائية .. انها الدارة الاكثر ابداعاً .. والتي صنعت بواسطة هذه الايدي الصغيرة
can build on their own.
دون أي مساعدة خارجية
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And so I want to do a little demo for you.
أريد ان اقدم لكم عرضاً صغيراً
So if I take this salt dough,
.. حسناً .. ان اخذتم الصلصال الملحي
again, it's like the play-dough you probably made as kids,
ومرة اخرى .. انه نفس الصلصال الذي يستخدمه اطفالكم للعب
and I plug it in --
و من ثم نوصله
it's a two-lead battery pack, simple battery pack,
انها بطارية .. بطارية بسيطة
you can buy them at Radio Shack
يمكن شراءها .. من راديو تشاك ..
and pretty much anywhere else --
او من اي مكان آخر
we can actually then
من ثم .. يمكننا ان
light things up.
نستخدم هذا ..لإضاءة المصابيح
But if any of you have studied electrical engineering,
ولكن ان كنت تدرس الهندسة الكهربائية
we can also create a short circuit.
يمكنك ان تصنع دارة كهربائية
If I push these together, the light turns off.
اذا ضغطت هنا .. سوف تنطفىء الاضواء
Right, the current wants to run through the play-dough, not through that LED.
نعم .. ان التيار الكهربائي يمر عبر الصلصال .. وليس من خلال الصمام
If I separate them again, I have some light.
وان فصلتهم مجددا .. سوف احصل على الضوء
Well now if I take that sugar dough,
والان ان اخذت صلصال السكر
the sugar dough doesn't want to conduct electricity.
فان صلصال السكر لن يسمح للتيار بالعبور ..
It's like a wall to the electricity.
انه يمثل عائق امام الكهرباء
If I place that between, now all the dough is touching,
وان وضعته هنا في المنتصف .. والان الصلصال متواصل فيما بينه
but if I stick that light back in,
وان وصلت الضوء اليه ..
I have light.
نرى انه يعمل ..
In fact, I could even add some movement to my sculptures.
في الحقيقة .. يمكن ان اضيف .. بعض اللمسات على " مجسمات الصلصال "
If I want a spinning tail, let's grab a motor,
وان أردت ذيلا دائرا .. سوف احضر محرك
put some play-dough on it, stick it on
ومن ثم اضع بعض العجين عليه .. اقوم بإيصاله
and we have spinning.
ومن ثم لدينا الذيل الدوار
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And once you have the basics,
و ما إن تتعلم الاساسيات
we can make a slightly more complicated circuit.
يمكنك ان تصنع دارات كهربائية معقدة اكثر
We call this our sushi circuit. It's very popular with kids.
نحن ندعوا هذه " دارة السوشي الكهربائية " .. انه معروفة بين طلابنا
I plug in again the power to it.
وها انا اصلها مجدد الى الكهرباء ..
And now I can start talking about parallel and series circuits.
والان يمكنني ان أبدأ الشرح عن الدارات الكهربائية المتوازية و المتتالية
I can start plugging in lots of lights.
يمكنني ان أصل الكثير من الاضواء
And we can start talking about things like electrical load.
ومن هنا يمكنني ان انطلق في الشرح عن الحمولة الكهربائية
What happens if I put in lots of lights
ماذا يحدث ان وضعنا الكثير من الانوار
and then add a motor?
ومن ثم وضعنا محرك ؟
It'll dim.
سوف تخفت الإضاءة
We can even add microprocessors
يمكننا اضافة معالجات مُصغرة
and have this as an input
وان نستخدمها كمدخلات بيانات ..
and create squishy sound music that we've done.
وان نصدر أصواتاً اسفنجية
You could do parallel and series circuits
يمكنان ان نقوم بالعديد من الدارات " المتوازية "
for kids using this.
لكي يتعلم الاطفال منها
So this is all in your home kitchen.
وكل هذا موجود في " مطبخك "
We've actually tried to turn it into an electrical engineering lab.
في الحقيقة حاولنا تحويل المطبخ الى مختبر هندسة كهربائية
We have a website, it's all there. These are the home recipes.
ولدينا موقع .. موضح عليه كل هذا .. ولدينا ايضاً وصفات ..
We've got some videos. You can make them yourselves.
لدينا ملفات فيديو .. يمكنكم ان تستخدموها لكي تقوم بكل هذا بأنفسكم
And it's been really fun since we put them up to see where these have gone.
لقد كانت خطوة رائعة ان نحمل هذه الوصفات والملفات لكي نرى تفاعل الناس
We've had a mom in Utah who used them with her kids,
لقد اخبرتنا أم من " يوتاوه انها تستخدم وصفاتنا مع اولادها ..
to a science researcher in the U.K.,
ولقد استخدمها باحثون في بريطانيا
and curriculum developers in Hawaii.
ومطوري المناهج في هاوايي
So I would encourage you all to grab some Play-Doh,
وانا احثكم على ان تحضروا بعضاً من الصلصال ..
grab some salt, grab some sugar and start playing.
وقليلاً من الملح والسكر .. وتبدأوا باللعب
We don't usually think of our kitchen as an electrical engineering lab
نحن عادة لا ننظر الى مطبخنا .. وكأنه مخبر هندسة كهربائية ..
or little kids as circuit designers,
ولا الى اطفالنا و كأنهم مصمموا دارات كهربائية
but maybe we should.
ولكن ربما يتوجب علينا ذلك
Have fun. Thank you.
إستمتعوا .. شُكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)